Cheng Ju

Mobile: (1) 510-316-0187, E-mail: jucheng1992@gmail.com
Github: https://github.com/jucheng1992 Home Page: https://jucheng1992.github.io/

SUMMARY

I am a second year PhD student in Biostatistics. My research interests mainly focus on machine learning and causal inference. My skill includes:

Proficient: R, Machine Learning, Causal Inference, Spark (pySpark)

Familiar: Python (numpy, scipy, pandas, scikit-learn, pySpark), SQL, Hadoop

EDUCATION

University of California, Berkeley, Berkeley, CA

August 2014 - May 2018 (expected)

PhD in Biostatistics

Statistical courses: Theoretical Statistics, Probability Theory, Applied Statistics, Statistical Computing, Advanced Learning Theory **Programming courses:** Data Structure, Efficient Algorithms and Intractable Problems

MOOC (find my certificates on my LinkedIn):

Introduction to Apache Spark; Scalable Machine Learning; Intro to Hadoop and MapReduce; Intro to Data Science

Southeast University, Nanjing, China

August 2010 - Jun 2014

Bachelor in Statistics

Related courses: Multivariate Statistical Analysis, Sampling Survey, Programming and Algorithmic Language

RELATED EXPERIENCE

Machine Learning and Ensemble Learning Method for Prediction of Propensity Score Research Assistant, University of California, Berkeley and Brigham and Women's Hospital

April 2015 - Present

The goal of this project is to improve the estimation of propensity score using machine learning methods.

• Compare machine learning algorithms (from *caret* library in R) and ensemble learning method for prediction of propensity score based on AUC and likelihood.

- Use high-dimensional propensity score method to generate new features from health claims data.
- Apply ensemble learning method and increase AUC from 0.79 to 0.83

Collaborative Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation for Large Scale and High Dimensional Data
April 2015 - Present

In this project we compare several causal models and develop variable selection method.

- Propose several pre-ordering method for variable selection of collaborative targeted maximum likelihood estimation (C-TMLE). Design different simulation cases to assess the performance of the pre-ordering methods.
- Study the performance of double robust estimators (A-IPTW, TMLE and C-TMLE) for correcting the bias of the estimation of target parameter in observation study using Monte Carlo simulation.
- This work was presented in 2015 Joint Statistical Meetings: Collaborative Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimator (C-TMLE) in Observational Studies.

Statistical Consultant, D-lab at University of California, Berkeley

January 2015 - August 2015

- Offer consulting service for statistical and machine learning problems. Including descriptive statistics, traditional statistical model (classical hypothesis tests, linear model) and machine learning (SVM, boosting, bagging, random forest).
- Previous projects including: PCA and visualization of high dimensional data; Penalized regression method (ridge regression and LASSO); Machine learning and model selection for prediction.

Organ Classification for Drosophila Embryo Image based on Machine Learning Method October 2015 - November 2015

This project mainly focuses on distinguish gut, yolk, and epidermal/mesodermal tissue in embryo images.

- Construct features from the raw embryo image based on computer vision method (e.g. Histogram oriented gradient feature and Local Binary Pattern) using *scikit-image* in python.
- Select features based on variable importance from Random Forest and Tree Boosting.
- Apply different machine learning algorithms (Random Forest, Tree boosting, Lasso, SVM) to classify the organ.
- Use cross-validation and Estimation Stability with Cross Validation (ESCV) to assess and select the models.

COMMUNICATION WORK EXPERIENCES

Graduate Student Instructor (Teaching Assistant), University of California, Berkeley

August 2014 - May 2015

- Teach the discussion class "Introduction to Probability and Statistics" and "Big Data in Public Health".
- Prepare materials for weekly discussion. Hold office hours to help students fully understand class materials.
- Give lecture about parallel programing in R using doParallel and foreach package.

SELECTED HONORS AND AWARDS

• The Taylor Award Scholarship, University of California, Berkeley, 2015.